[insects chittering]
[rumbling]
[rumbling intensifies]
[train whistle blows in distance]
[rumbling]
[dishes rattling]
[train rattling in distance]
It's coming! It's coming!
It's coming! Come on!
[man 1] The earth is shaking!
[panting] It's here!
[woman] What's here?
- [man 2] Calm down!
- The ground is moving!
- What's coming? What is it?
- A beast.
Like a beast that's pulling a town.
- [train whistle blows in distance]
- [rumbling]
It's here.
[dogs barking in distance]
[train whistle blows in distance]
Hey. kid. come on.
Come on. You're gonna miss it.
Mama Úrsula.
[chuckles] It's here.
What is here?
[clavichord music playing]
[man] Hurry up. run!
[woman] It's here! It's here!
- Meme. leave that. Come on.
- [Fernanda] Where are you going?
It's almost here.
May we go. Mama?
You may. after your lesson. Renata.
Fernanda. let her go.
Can I go. Mama?
Let's go. let's go. let's go.
- [young José Arcadio] Careful. Meme. Wait.
- Come on. come on. come on.
Grab my arm. Grab my arm!
Less talking. more moving.
- Grab my arm.
- [Úrsula] For goodness' sake. Careful.
- [Aureliano II] Forget the shawl.
- [Úrsula] Don't take off your shawl.
- [door slams]
- [Úrsula] Remedios!
Remedios! Put this on.
[train whistle blowing in distance]
[woman] Come on. children. Come quick!
[narrator] The innocent train
that would bring to Macondo
so many uncertainties and truths.
so much praise and misfortune.
and so many changes. calamities.
and longings had finally arrived.
[train rattling]
[Aureliano II] Welcome to Macondo!
[exclaims excitedly]
[narrator] The people of Macondo watched
as José Arcadio Segundo
and Aureliano Triste
waved from the top of the locomotive.
[screams joyfully]
- You're here. brother! You're here!
- Isn't this amazing?
- Uncle!
- Where is he?
[man 1] It's here! We did it. Macondo!
[man 2] Welcome to Macondo!
[dramatic music playing]
Your great-grandfather
would be so proud. José Arcadio.
You made his lifelong dream come true.
You connected Macondo with the world.
Well done. son.
Now. you really have proven
half of the town wrong. brother.
It was worth the wait. wasn't it?
- Come on. Where are we going?
- To the train.
No. Meme.
- Come on. Let's go on the train.
- Stop. no. No.
- Mom is going to get angry.
- So what? Don't be dumb.
No. Meme. Where are we going?
[man 1] Welcome to Macondo. Welcome.
[woman] Hello.
[man 2] I'm sorry. I've just arrived…
Nothing to worry about!
Nothing to worry about.
ladies and gentlemen! That's right!
Come on closer. Don't be afraid.
[narrator] A stranger
stepped off the train
so elegant and dignified
that Pietro Crespi himself
would have looked like a fop beside him.
[dramatic music continues]
Ah. pardon me.
Uh. mind telling me
where I could find a good restaurant?
A new restaurant
that has authentic and traditional food.
I know just the place. Mr…
Herbert.
Mr. Herbert. I would like to invite you
over for lunch at my house.
where the finest food in all of Macondo
is prepared.
- Isn't that right. Mama Úrsula?
- That's right.
The Buendía house opens its doors
for this special occasion.
- How wonderful.
- [Úrsula] Everyone is welcome.
- Our doors are open.
- [Mr. Herbert] Thank you so much.
[conductor] Next stop. Fundación!
[indistinct chattering]
I found these two sitting
in the back of the train.
Thank you so much. Miss. uh…
Cotes.
[Petra] Mm.
Dad. who's that woman?
Why does she know us?
Son. everybody here knows us.
We are Buendías.
- [Amaranta] José Arcadio.
- You…
- You disappeared. Where'd you go?
- Why'd you run off?
[young José Arcadio] It was Meme.
She dragged me onto the train. I swear.
Welcome. Welcome to the Buendía household.
Santa Sofía. go get two hens
from the back. please.
We have to cook a bit of everything.
You never know what foreigners
are going to want to eat.
[Mr. Herbert] Wow.
This place is like a dream.
[clavichord music playing]
[woman] Right over there.
[José Arcadio II] Rum.
Welcome. Welcome to our home.
Have some rum.
Welcome to the Buendía household.
[man] Thank you.
[Fernanda] Aureliano?
[man coughs]
Aureliano?
- [woman 2] Oh. she's playing great. Wow!
- Renata! Go to your room right now.
- [woman 2] Why is she stopping?
- Aureliano?
[woman 3] Do you think
there's sleeping beds here?
[Fernanda] José Arcadio!
[scoffs] Of course it was you
who brought this circus into the house.
This circus is the future.
And this is just the beginning.
so you might wanna get used to it.
'Cause I am not my brother.
[woman 4] Mrs. Buendía. how many people
are you having over for lunch?
[José Arcadio II] Welcome.
[Úrsula] We'll need the other set
for this many people.
José Arcadio. leave that. Come.
[Úrsula] That one. Bring me that.
[Amaranta] Tell your mother
her reign is over.
The Buendía house is chaotic once again.
Mama. my aunt says
your reign is over and that--
José Arcadio.
- Go to your mom.
- [Fernanda] Aureliano.
[intriguing music playing]
- [all gasp]
- Oh. it startled me.
[laughter]
Take me as your husband. I beg you.
[chuckles] That's a crazy thing to say.
I promise you
that I will spend my entire life
doing everything in my power
to give the world to you.
How will you do that?
You don't know anything about me. do you?
Remedios.
Go to the kitchen.
Aren't you going to eat something?
It's going to get cold.
Well. gentlemen.
the bell rings only once for supper
and once for Mass.
- Thank you.
- Thank you. ma'am.
[José Arcadio II] Please enjoy. everybody.
It's delicious. You're gonna love it.
[indistinct chattering]
[José Arcadio II] Enjoy. everybody.
[Mr. Herbert] Wow. this is really good.
[woman] José Arcadio.
bring some more juice.
[man 2] Delicious.
[woman 2] Chicken?
[José Arcadio II] Poulet?
Oh. pass her the chicken. please.
[man 3 belches. groans]
[Mr. Herbert] Oh!
What is this?
Banana.
- You eat it.
- You eat it?
Mm-hmm.
Banana. anyone?
[bird chirping]
[dramatic music playing]
ONE HUNDRED YEARS OF SOLITUDE
[José Arcadio II]
You can find these things everywhere.
and they grow very quickly.
[Mr. Herbert] Remarkable.
Uh. um. do you know where there's more?
Oh. I'm happy to take you
all over the outskirts of Macondo.
It's full of bananas.
Much appreciated. young man.
Yeah. my pleasure.
[Aureliano] Who brought these gringos
into this house?
[guests murmuring]
- Get out of here!
- [José Arcadio II] Hey. settle down. sir.
The thing is
that all of these nice travelers here
are Great-Grandmother's guests.
Go talk to her.
This is the last thing
I need to see in Macondo.
Our house getting invaded
by the same sons of bitches
that stole Panama from us.
[woman] What does he mean "Panama"?
[Aureliano] Bastards.
- Úrsula!
- Please excuse the old man. He's. uh…
Well. he's lost his mind.
He couldn't kill himself
and leave us in peace!
Uh…
No. it's really no problem at all.
I'm loving Macondo.
Everyone is. uh. very passionate.
It's very pretty.
I told you. They grow everywhere.
- Oh my goodness.
- [intriguing music playing]
Oh my goodness. Would you look…
So many.
Who owns all of it?
Oh. it's everyone's.
- All of it?
- Mm-hmm. The people's.
[train whistle blowing]
[narrator] The arrival of the train
unleashed a wave of excitement
no one could contain.
[music intensifies]
- [Fernanda] Renata!
- [gasps]
You are not to be outside
when those people are here.
- Go to your room!
- [Sofía] Everybody. this way. please.
We call that "papoche."
We throw those to the animals.
This one is delicious.
Incredibly sweet. hmm?
[narrator] The people of Macondo
surrendered to the endless bounty
that came in the train cars…
[conductor] How are you doing?
We can barely keep up.
Look at what I brought for the kids.
…while foreigners found themselves
in a land
where everything seemed to flourish
without measure.
[lively music playing]
Hide all of it. son.
Fernanda has the kids
locked in their room.
It's beautiful. sure.
- Yeah.
- But it's a plague.
[Mr. Herbert] Mm-hmm. Okay.
[lively music continues]
It's beautiful.
Paradise.
[music stops]
[José Arcadio II] Colonel!
[Aureliano] Mmm.
Did you know that aside from the food.
foreigners come to this house
to meet the family's madman?
You're a real tourist attraction.
You think everything
that's happening in Macondo
is just fine and wonderful. José Arcadio.
because you're too stupid to see it.
You don't understand
who the gringos really are.
You have to change your tune
because the gringos are here to stay.
Mr. Herbert told me
some merchants were coming from Ohio.
and that they're buying
every single vacant lot around Macondo.
Well. they'll find out
who really owns those lots.
Imbecile.
You old bastard.
[insects chittering]
[door hinge creaking]
[dark music playing]
[in Wayuu] What do you want?
Get out of here.
[in English] Rebeca.
[narrator] The colonel
immediately recognized his sister Rebeca.
the one with the impatient heart
and the boundless womb.
The only one with the unbridled courage
Úrsula had always wished
to see in her bloodline.
[Aureliano] I thought you were dead.
If we had known you were--
Aureliano… I don't give a shit
about what happens
beyond the walls of this house.
And what happens to the Buendías
matters even less.
To me. it's as if
the family died with José Arcadio.
Tell me once and for all
why you've come here.
or I'll shoot your head off.
The land that surrounds Macondo.
I know Arcadio gave those property titles
to my brother.
And if those lands have rightful owners.
meaning you and José Arcadio.
the gringos can't even go near them.
So if you still have those somewhere--
I burned everything
when your brother died.
All I kept of his…
was this house.
and this shotgun in my hands.
[Aureliano] Hmm.
It was nice to see you. Rebeca.
Mm.
[door hinge creaking]
[door closes]
[reverential music playing]
[Fernanda in Latin]
"And renew the right spirit within me."
"Do not cast me away from your face."
"And take not thy Holy Spirit from me."
[in English] After having sinned.
David asks God to give him a pure heart.
Because God always knows
when we have sinned.
[in Latin] "Restore to me
the joy of your salvation."
[knocking at door]
"Strengthen me with your spirit."
[music stops]
[in English] The last guest just left.
Can I go pee. Mom?
Be careful. Meme.
[footsteps rapidly thumping]
Don't you want to rest for a bit.
José Arcadio?
My son knows that he has to take
his education very seriously
if he wants to go to Rome.
But it is impossible to do so
when this house is full of sinful men
day and night
who may lead him down the path of evil.
It is a Christian value
to help those who are in need.
It's in the Bible.
They are vagabonds. Úrsula.
They're taking advantage of you.
and you seem to like that.
Don't forget
you are in my house. Fernanda.
I opened my doors to those foreigners
with the same generosity as I did for you.
And all of your saints.
Come to think of it.
today is October 4th…
which just so happens to be the day
of the loved Saint Francis of Assisi.
The saint of poverty…
and humility.
[dark ethereal music playing]
[Aureliano] She's alive. Mama.
She's alive.
[Úrsula] God forgive me.
[music fades]
[sobs] What kind of mother
would neglect their child all these years?
Did you know she was alive?
[young José Arcadio]
Auntie. I was looking for you.
[Amaranta chuckles]
[narrator] The only one who never forgot.
even for a single minute.
that Rebeca was alive.
rotting in a soup of maggots.
was the ruthless and aging Amaranta.
She thought of her at dawn.
and every time she changed.
the black bandage of terrible atonement
wrapped around her hand.
[mysterious music playing]
[Aureliano II] After saving
an entire village of people.
all who hadn't slept for months.
I decided to write that book.
[young Meme] What's it about?
[Aureliano II] I cannot tell you.
beautiful Meme.
No one must understand its meaning.
not until 100 years have passed.
[laughter]
- [music stops]
- [Aureliano II clears throat]
And why are you dressed like that?
He's telling us the story of Melquiades.
Can't say I'm surprised. Renata.
Sin has always come naturally to you.
But you. José Arcadio.
I would have never expected you--
I went and woke them up.
Don't reprimand them.
For years. I allowed you
to humiliate and abandon us.
Do you know where
your children are eating now?
In their quarters. like a pair of dogs.
Because. apparently. Úrsula's guests
are far more important than any of us are.
Stop being so dramatic. Fernanda.
[Fernanda] You do nothing for us.
And meanwhile. you get it all.
Even your little concubine.
What is a concubine?
It's the lady that we met
at the train station that day.
[woman] You'll be begging for forgiveness!
[narrator] That same day.
Fernanda sent Aureliano's trunk of clothes
to his concubine's house.
She sent them in broad daylight.
and ordered that they'd be carried
down the middle of the street
for everyone to see…
[woman 2] How shameless.
…believing that her wayward husband
would be unable to bear the shame
and would return home
with his head hung low.
[laughing]
[woman 3] Shameful. Both of them.
You're disgraceful!
[woman 2] What a dog!
[man 1] You have no shame.
[people murmuring]
[mysterious music playing]
[overhead clattering]
[man pants] Remedios.
What are you doing up there?
I don't know what's wrong with me.
All I think about is seeing you.
You should get down.
The roof's not safe.
Let me put soap on your back at least.
I don't think anyone's ever put soap
on their back.
[screams]
[loud thud]
[dark music playing]
[Úrsula] Good heavens!
Remedios.
[train whistle blowing]
[whistle blows]
[Mr. Herbert] Oh. here he is.
Welcome to Macondo. Mr. Brown.
- Mr. Herbert. how you doing?
- Great. great. great.
This is the town's new mayor.
At your service. Mr. Brown.
- Nice to meet you. sir.
- Sir.
Now. if you come this way. we'll. uh…
Is it always this hot?
It's hotter than Hades.
Oh. it certainly is.
but you do get used to it.
- Okay. I hope so.
- And it's…
Uh. the train is new to town. so…
- It might feel…
- No. no. no. no. no.
[narrator] Mr. Jack Brown arrived
in Macondo on a hot Wednesday.
straight from Prattville. Alabama.
He was followed everywhere
by a pack of ferocious hounds.
engineers. topographers.
and land surveyors.
Nobody knew what they were looking for.
- Go ahead and set that down there.
- Sir. it's ready.
Take my cane. Thank you.
[narrator] Endowed with resources
that in a different era
would have been reserved
only for divine providence…
José Arcadio! My horse!
…the foreigners altered
the rainfall patterns.
moved the river
from where it had always been.
and put it on the other side of the town.
And at the newly established
banana business. the United Fruit Company.
José Arcadio Segundo
found work as a foreman.
[José Arcadio II] Gentlemen! Welcome!
In the coming days. you will all discover
that the working conditions we offer
are the best you'll find along the coast.
Because our company
is the largest company there is
in the whole area.
We take care of the entire process.
from the moment we cut the banana
to its exportation.
[indistinct chattering]
Part of your compensation
is issued in these vouchers.
which are redeemable
at the town's local commissary
for imported products such as these.
You should all feel privileged
because there is no place in Macondo
or in the entire country
where you can get the best quality
ham products from Virginia.
This here is our gift to you
for your loyal service.
[cheering]
[suspenseful music playing]
- José Arcadio.
- Mr. Brown.
[José Arcadio II] Please enjoy it.
Explore the town and get some rest
because tomorrow
we start bright and early at 6:00.
So welcome to the United Fruit Family!
[cheering]
- [man] Looks good.
- [José Arcadio II] Welcome.
Hey. go grab some ham. It's American.
Welcome. Welcome.
[ethereal music playing]
[narrator] Until her very last minute
on Earth.
Remedios the Beauty remained unaware
that her inescapable
and unsettling female nature
was a daily disaster.
[indistinct chattering]
[José Arcadio II] The bananas are
transported along these rails to the exit.
From there. they're taken to the train
and from the train to the port.
where the bananas are loaded
onto company ships.
[ethereal music continues]
[wind whistling]
[rattling]
[rattling stops]
[music swells]
[train whistle blowing]
Hello. good afternoon.
[unsettling ethereal music playing]
[insects chittering]
[narrator] From the moment
Remedios stepped onto the plantation.
the air was impregnated
with a deadly fragrance.
The men working in the ditches
felt possessed by a strange fascination.
threatened by an invisible danger.
and many succumbing
to the terrible urge to weep.
- [man 1] Get back!
- [men grunting]
[man 2] Let go!
- [man 3] What do you think you're doing?
- [men scream]
- [panting]
- [music fades]
[José Arcadio II]
And that's extremely important to us
because we have to deliver them
perfectly clean.
What did you think of the tour?
[Úrsula] I would've never imagined
that you could have this many
in one place.
Darling! What happened? What's wrong?
Why don't you have your hat. Remedios?
[Úrsula] Oh my God. Remedios.
Come on. boys.
[man] Let's go. let's go. let's go!
Grab your machetes!
[tense percussive music playing]
[music fades]
[Mr. Brown] My best whiskey.
Directly from Canada.
- Pretty smooth. huh?
- [laughs]
Did your family enjoy the visit?
[José Arcadio II] Mm.
[in Spanish] That's good.
[José Arcadio II in English] Yes.
Except two of my men died
on the plantation today.
An accident.
Well. that's very sad to hear.
Got any more news to share?
More men keep coming.
We're starting with two full crews
tomorrow morning.
We'll need to expand the barracks.
These boys are coming from far away.
We'll take care of that.
Anything else?
Yes. Mr. Brown.
We should build a health center here
for emergencies.
like the one we had today.
It's a good idea.
I'll make sure they see to that.
Oh. Buendía. Hang on a sec.
Take these.
Some nice coupons for the commissary.
Good job. Buendía.
Honey. could you come in here a second?
[José Arcadio II] Mm.
Sir?
[young Meme] Does it hurt. Auntie?
Why did they do that to you?
[Aureliano] Because the people
in this town are going mad.
[Fernanda] It's not just that.
It's because Remedios is provocative.
We've seen how she walks around naked
with no sense of modesty
so that the men Great-Grandmother
invites over can gawk at her.
[Aureliano] Hey! Show some respect.
you ungrateful city brat.
Modesty is for people like you. Fernanda.
who have to pray day and night
to drive the evil out of their souls.
I'm just telling the truth.
Your aunt isn't just crazy.
She's extremely dangerous.
[knocking at door]
[man] Mail!
[door opens]
[young José Arcadio]
Presents from Grandpa. Come on. Meme!
[man] We'll put it here.
[young José Arcadio] Wait. Meme. Hold it.
Whoa.
I wanna see what it is.
[young José Arcadio pants. sobs]
[young Meme screams]
[children crying]
- [Fernanda crying]
- [somber music playing]
[screams] No!
[in Spanish] My dad! [sobs]
[somber music continues]
[music stops]
[dramatic music playing]
[music turns lively]
[in English] Get out!
[music stops]
How could you tarnish my father's memory
in such a horrible way?
A Christian man has died. Aureliano.
A man. not a dog!
[murmuring]
This is our homage to your father.
Ma. I didn't do anything.
It was Meme and Papa.
Shut up. you snitch.
[Úrsula] Fernanda. it wasn't just him.
- It was also my idea--
- Stay out of it. please. Úrsula.
It's not your concern.
I accepted this failed marriage for you
and everyone's gross incivility
so I could raise my children
in a Christian household.
But I've come to realize
that. time and time again.
in this insane house. it's impossible.
The children are leaving Macondo!
You can't take my children.
I can
because I am their mama.
And it's them I chose.
But not you. You chose her instead.
[melancholy music playing]
[Úrsula] For God's sake. Fernanda.
How can you say that?
I packed you all of your favorite treats.
But you shouldn't eat them
all at once. all right?
You promise me?
Well. come here. Let's get you changed.
- Come on.
- [sobs]
[Úrsula sobs]
It's beautiful.
Thank you so much.
[young Meme] Auntie.
aren't you coming to the station?
I love you very much.
Have fun. okay?
[young José Arcadio]
I'm going to miss you.
Me too.
José Arcadio. Let's go. sweetheart.
[reverential music playing]
Auntie. are you feeling all right?
I've never felt better.
[reverential music continues]
I went through this myself. you know.
But you and I came from royalty. Renata.
- All queens are educated by nuns.
- [whistle blows]
It's what's best for you.
[train whistle blows]
[whistle blows]
- I'm gonna miss you. my love.
- Me too. Daddy.
- Be a good girl.
- Okay.
[sobs]
Go with Grandma.
- [whistle blows]
- [Úrsula] Oh. Meme.
[bell rings]
[melancholy music playing]
[sniffles]
[Úrsula] May God be with you. my children.
Be a good girl. you hear me. Meme?
Write me a letter every month.
Daddy will be right here.
reading your letters.
Don't ever forget that Daddy loves you.
and that I'll be right here
waiting for you to come back!
[steam hissing]
[music fades]
NEW RAILWAYS
WILL BOOST DEVELOPMENT IN MACONDO
[Aureliano] My family
has lost their minds.
Now it turns out
Macondo is going to have a pope
and a saint.
Mm.
And a martyr.
[Aureliano] Hmm.
[Gerineldo] Haven't you seen it yet?
[dark melancholy music playing]
Mm-mm.
IN MEMORY OF COLONEL AURELIANO BUENDÍA
TIRELESS DEFENDER OF FREEDOM AND JUSTICE
HIS FIGHT FOR A SOVEREIGN NATION
ENDURES IN THE HEARTS OF HIS PEOPLE
[Aureliano] I guess
since they couldn't kill me…
they wanna bury me alive. Gerineldo.
[Aureliano] Mm.
[indistinct chattering]
[car horn honks]
[Aureliano] What's the matter with you?
What's the hurry?
Gerineldo. look at the mess
we've gotten ourselves into.
All because we invited those fucking
banana-eating gringos into our town.
- [jazz music playing]
- [car horn honks]
[indistinct chattering]
- Here you go.
- [officer] You work here. old man?
[man] My son-in-law does.
The father of my grandson.
[officer] You can't come in
unless you work here.
This is for company workers only.
But I have a voucher.
and the man who gave it to me works here.
- Show me the voucher.
- You cannot forbid me to come in.
- Show me the voucher. old man.
- Here's the voucher.
You shouldn't have this. This is illegal.
What you are doing is illegal.
You're nobody here.
You don't have any authority.
Put that back!
Hey. he's trying to steal this!
- Manuel! Hey. don't touch him!
- Come here!
[old man] Leave him alone!
- Leave him alone! Manuel!
- [Manuel] Grandpa. help!
[officer] Don't move! Shut up!
[old man] Manuel!
What have you done?
- [blows land]
- [old man grunts]
[blow lands]
[Aureliano] Scum!
Murderers!
You bastards!
Come on.
[unsettling music playing]
What's the matter with them?
[people murmuring]
What have we done?
Come on. let's go.
Please. Aureliano.
What's happening. Gerineldo?
[dark ethereal music playing]
[officer] Hey. sir!
Hey. where are you going? Sir!
Hey!
[music fades]
What are you doing here. Colonel?
I'm gonna tell that guy Mr. Brown
that a murder was committed
by his own company.
By United Fruit Co.?
I suggest you get out of my way
if you don't want trouble.
[guard] Everything all right?
[José Arcadio II] Everything's fine.
- The Conservative government…
- As I was saying. Mr. Brown…
Huh? What's going on?
[Aureliano] And what's worse.
they gave you free rein
to do whatever you want!
But know that here in Macondo.
there are still men
that will never kneel to anyone
and that are willing and ready to revolt.
This time. against you
and your murderous organization.
[Aureliano groans]
[Aureliano scoffs] You bastards.
- The hell's going on?
- Don't worry. Everything's fine.
[guard] What did he want?
[dark piano music playing]
[people murmuring]
[music intensifies]
[narrator] Úrsula was the only one
with enough serenity to understand
the nature of that irreparable wind.
She watched Remedios the Beauty.
amid the dazzling flutter of the sheets
rising with her.
passing through the sky
where the four o'clock light
came to an end.
as she disappeared forever
into the atmosphere.
where not even the highest birds of memory
could reach her.
[music fades]
[soft melodic music playing]
[dark percussive music playing]
[music fades]
[percussive ethereal music playing]
[dark percussive music playing]
[music fades]
[ethereal melancholy music playing]